Inventory of the William Van Til papers
Hoover Institution Archives
William Van Til papers
1928-1997
89015
Van Til, William.
59 manuscript boxes (23.6 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
The William Van Til papers document the career of an important figure in the history of American education in the twentieth century. Identified with the progressive movement of John Dewey and William Heard Kilpatrick, Van Til was an early supporter of racial integration in American schools and a proponent of the use of a multicultural curriculum in the classroom. The bulk of the Van Til papers consist of his speeches and writings, along with correspondence between Van Til and his publishers.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1989.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
1911 Born, Corona, New York
1933 Awarded B.A. degree, Columbia College
1934-1943 Instructor and assistant professor, College of Education, Ohio State University
1935 Awarded M. A. degree, Columbia University
1946 Receives doctorate, Ohio State University
1947-1951 Professor, University of Illinois
1951-1957 Professor, George Peabody College
1957-1967 Professor and administrator, New York University
1961-1962 President, Association for Supervision and Curriculum Development
1964-1966 President, John Dewey Society
1967-1968 President, National Society of College Teachers of Education
1967-1977 Professor, School of Education, Indiana State University
2006 Died
Scope and Content of Collection
The William Van Til papers document the career of an important figure in the history of American education in the twentieth century. Identified with the progressive movement of John Dewey and William Heard Kilpatrick, Van Til was an early supporter of racial integration in American schools and a proponent of the use of a multicultural curriculum in the classroom. The bulk of the Van Til papers consist of his speeches and writings, along with correspondence between Van Til and his publishers. A prolific author, William Van Til outlined his views on education and society in numerous articles written for academic journals and magazines. Many of these articles are concerned with the response of the American educational system to the challenge of rapid social change, and of how schools address questions of diversity and inclusiveness. An advocate of a holistic approach to education, Van Til thought that the mission of schools included the transmission of democratic values and the preparation of students to participate as citizens in wider society. Van Til's books include ones devoted to secondary education and to the modernization of curriculum in American schools. Another of his books is addressed to writers and offers them advice on how to develop their skills in order to have their work published. Van Til also wrote an extensive autobiography, and drafts of the two editions of this work are part of the collection. Additionally, the papers contain a number of unpublished stories that Van Til wrote in his youth.
The papers also include materials relating to a number of professional organizations that Van Til belonged to, as well as to writing workshops that he conducted. There are also some studies that Van Til collaborated on, including surveys of school systems in Iran, Puerto Rico, and the Virgin Islands.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Education--United States.; School integration--United States.; Teachers--Training of--United States.
Collection Contents
- Speeches and Writings, 1938-1987
  - Curriculum: Quest for Relevance, 1970-1976
    - Reviews, 1971-1975 (Folder 1: 1-13)
    - Correspondence, 1969-1976 (Folder 1: 14-16)
    - Outline, 1974 (Folder 1: 17)
    - Permissions, 1970-1974 (Folder 1: 18-21)
    - Revision, 1974 (Folder 1: 22)
    - Comment, 1975 (Folder 1: 23)
    - Galley proofs, 1973-1974 (Folder 2: 1-2)
  - Education: A Beginning, 1969-1976
    - Articles relating to subject matter of book, arranged by chapter heading, 1975-1976 (Folder 2: 3-15)
    - Articles relating to subject matter of book, arranged by chapter heading, 1975-1976 (Folder 3: 1-8)
    - General correspondence, 1969-1971 (Folder 3: 9)
    - Permissions, 1973 (Folder 3: 10)
    - Critics, 1972-1973 (Folder 3: 11)
    - Reviews, 1971-1975 (Folder 3: 12-15)
    - Corrections, 1971-1972 (Folder 3: 16)
    - Printed copies, 1971-1974
      - First edition, 1971 (Folder 4: 1)
      - Second edition, 1974 (Folder 4: 2)
      - Unbound chapters, 1974 (Folder 4: 3)
    - Galley proofs, 1974 (Folder 5: 1)
  - Secondary Education: School and Community, 1966-1978
    - Galley proofs, 1978 (Folder 5: 2)
    - First draft, 1976 (Folder 6: 1)
    - Charts, 1976 (Folder 6: 2)
    - Micellaneous, 1976 (Folder 6: 3)
    - Not used, 1976 (Folder 6: 4)
    - Second draft, 1977 (Folder 7: 1-12)
    - Research materials, 1966-1977 (Folder 7: 13-14)
    - Research materials, 1966-1977 (Folder 8: 1-12)
    - Illustrations, 1977 (Folder 8: 13-16)
    - Corrections, 1977 (Folder 8: 17)
    - Footnotes, 1977 (Folder 8: 18-20)
    - Forematter, 1977 (Folder 8: 21)
    - Further readings, 1977 (Folder 8: 22)
    - Instructor's manual, 1977 (Folder 9: 1)
    - Involvement and discussion, 1977 (Folder 9: 2)
    - Permissions, 1976-1977 (Folder 9: 3-4)
    - Prospectus, 1977 (Folder 9: 5)
    - Pictures, 1977 (Folder 9: 6)
    - Readers, 1977 (Folder 9: 7)
    - Responses to queries, 1977 (Folder 9: 8)
    - Reviews, 1976-1977 (Folder 9: 9)
    - Galley proofs, 1978 (Folder 9: 10)
    - Table of contents, 1977 (Folder 10: 1)
    - Suggestions for art work, 1977 (Folder 10: 2)
    - Update, 1977 (Folder 10: 3)
    - Corrected draft, 1977 (Folder 10: 5-6)
  - Issues in Secondary Education, yearbook of the National Society for the Study of Education, 1973-1976
    - Correspondence, 1973-1976
      - Passow, Harry, 1975-1976 (Folder 11: 1)
      - Rehage, Kenneth J., 1973-1976 (Folder 11: 2)
    - Talks, 1975-1976 (Folder 11: 3)
    - Yearbook committee, 1973-1974 (Folder 11: 4)
    - Miscellaneous, 1973-1975 (Folder 11: 5)
    - Manuscript guide, 1973 (Folder 11: 6)
    - Proposal, 1973 (Folder 11: 7)
    - Proofs, 1975 (Folder 11: 8)
    - Proposal, 1973 (Folder 12: 1)
    - Drafts, 1975 (Folder 12: 2-15)
    - Drafts, 1975 (Folder 13: 1-8)
    - Drafts, 1975 (Folder 14: 1-13)
    - Writing for Professional Publication, 1976-1986
  - Schedule, 1979-1980 (Folder 15: 1)
    - Permissions, 1979-1980 (Folder 15: 2)
    - Proofs, 1980 (Folder 15: 3)
    - Drafts, 1980 (Folder 15: 4-12)
    - Drafts, 1980 (Folder 16: 1-24)
    - Drafts, 1980 (Folder 17: 1-6)
    - Research materials, 1979-1980 (Folder 18: 1-30)
    - Correspondence with Roy Van Til, 1979 (Folder 18: 31)
    - First draft, 1979 (Folder 19: 1)
    - Editing, 1979 (Folder 19: 2)
    - Permissions, 1979-1980 (Folder 19: 3)
    - Proofs, 1980 (Folder 19: 4)
    - Proofs, 1980 (Folder 20: 1-3)
    - Resources, 1976-1980 (Folder 21: 1-2)
    - Queries, 1982-1983 (Folder 21: 3)
    - Reviews by readers, 1982-1983 (Folder 21: 4)
    - Supplements, 1977 (Folder 21: 5)
    - Word processor, 1983-1984 (Folder 21: 6)
    - Letters, 1980-1981 (Folder 21: 7)
    - Miscellaneous, 1979 (Folder 21: 8)
    - Orders, 1984-1985 (Folder 22: 1)
    - Possible inclusions in revised edition, 1979-1984 (Folder 22: 2)
    - Correspondence, 1979-1985 (Folder 22: 3-4)
    - Reviews, 1980-1982 (Folder 22: 5-6)
    - Promotion, 1980-1981 (Folder 22: 7)
    - Database service, 1982 (Folder 22: 8)
    - Contracts, 1979-1987 (Folder 23: 1)
  - ACSD in Retrospect, printed copy and correspondence, 1985-1986 (Folder 23: 2)
  - Democracy Demands It, comments by others, 1950 (Folder 23: 3)
  - The Danube Flows through Fascism, correspondence, 1938 (Folder 23: 4)
  - Economic Roads for American Democracy, correspondence, 1947-1950 (Folder 23: 5)
  - Great Human Issues of Our Times, drafts, 1953-1956 (Folder 23: 6-7)
  - High Schools of the Future, correspondence, draft, and printed copy, 1968-1969 (Folder 23: 8)
  - Humanizing Education, draft and printed copy, 1967 (Folder 23: 9)
  - Education: A Beginning, printed excerpt, 1974 (Folder 23: 10)
  - The Making of a Modern Educator, 1959-1961
    - Correspondence, 1961 (Folder 23: 11)
    - Draft, 1959 (Folder 23: 12)
    - Draft, 1959 (Folder 24: 1)
    - Review, 1961 (Folder 24: 2)
  - Modern Education for the Junior High School Years, drafts, 1961 (Folder 24:)
  - My Way of Looking at It: An Autobiography, review, 1984 (Folder 24: 3)
  - Time on Your Hands, printed copy, 1945 (Folder 24: 4)
  - A Wide Wide World, draft, 1974 (Folder 24: 5)
  - Secondary Education: School and Community, 1978-1979
    - Reviews, 1978 (Folder 24: 6)
    - Research materials, 1978-1979 (Folder 24: 7-19)
  - Americans All, draft and printed copy of chapter, 1942 (Folder 24: 20)
  - Education for Democratic Citizenship, printed copy of chapter and clipping, 1951 (Folder 24: 21)
  - Democratic Human Relations, draft of chapter, 1945 (Folder 24: 22)
  - Educational Freedom in an Age of Anxiety, correspondence and drafts of foreword and introduction, 1953 (Folder 24: 23)
  - "Rights and Responsibilities as Citizens and Teachers," printed copy, 1960 (Folder 24: 24)
  - Forces Affecting American Education, draft, 1953
    - Draft, 1953 (Folder 24: 25)
    - Draft, 1953 (Folder 25: 1-3)
  - Intercultural Attitudes in the Making, correspondence, 1946 (Folder 25: 4)
  - Leadership through Supervision, drafts of chapter, 1946 (Folder 25: 5)
  - Role of Supervisor and Curriculum Director in a Climate of Change, printed copy of chapter, 1965 (Folder 25: 6)
  - The Study and Teaching of American History, correspondence and printed copy of chapter, 1946 (Folder 25: 7)
  - America's Stake in Human Rights, correspondence and draft of preface, 1949 (Folder 25: 8)
  - Another Way of Looking at It, 1974
    - Printed copy, 1974 (Folder 25: 9)
    - Responses and reactions, 1974-1975 (Folder 25: 10)
  - Consumer Education and the Social Studies, printed copy, 1945 (Folder 25: 11)
  - Curriculum Frontiers of the 1960s, printed copy, 1963 (Folder 25: 12)
  - The Development of Education for Desegregation and Integration, 1965 (Folder 25: 13)
  - Resources for Writing for Publication in Education, draft of foreward, 1950 (Folder 26: 1)
  - One Way of Looking at It, 1971
    - Printed copy, 1971 (Folder 26: 2)
    - Orders and requests, 1971 (Folder 26: 3)
    - Comments, 1971 (Folder 26: 4)
  - The Laboratory School: Its Rise and Fall? correspondence and printed copy, 1969 (Folder 26: 5)
  - "Laboratory Schools and the National Reports," draft and printed copy, 1987 January (Folder 26: 6)
  - Ethnic Modification of the Curriculum, printed copy, 1969 (Folder 26: 7)
- Organizations, 1967-1991
  - Associated Organizations for Teacher Education, 1968
    - General, 1973 (Folder 26: 8)
    - Educational Technology Committee, 1968-1970 (Folder 26: 9)
    - Commission on Issues, 1973 (Folder 27: 1)
    - Term, 1972-1973 (Folder 27: 2)
    - Relations with Society of Professors of Education, 1973 (Folder 27: 3)
    - Advisory Council, 1972-1973 (Folder 27: 4)
  - Society of Professors of Education, 1967-1991
    - Monograph series, 1985-1986 (Folder 27: 5)
    - Occasional papers, 1974-1976 (Folder 27: 6)
    - Occasional papers, 1974-1975 (Folder 28: 1)
    - Newsletters, 1967-1975 (Folder 28: 2)
    - Archival, 1969-1971 (Folder 28: 3)
    - Major papers and abstracts, 1971 (Folder 28: 4)
    - General, 1970-1991 (Folder 28: 5)
  - National Society of College Teachers of Education, 1967-1969
    - Correspondence, 1967-1969
      - General, 1968-1969 (Folder 28: 6)
      - Bayles, Ernest E., 1968-1969 (Folder 28: 7)
      - Pomeroy, Edward C., 1967-1968 (Folder 28: 8)
    - Program and schedule, 1968 (Folder 28: 9)
    - Expenses, 1967-1969 (Folder 29: 1)
    - Terre Haute meeting, 1968 (Folder 29: 2)
    - Newsletters, 1967-1969 (Folder 29: 3)
    - Executive Board and minutes, 1967-1969 (Folder 29: 4)
  - National Society for the Study of Education, correspondence, 1977-1982 (Folder 29: 5)
- Speeches and Writings, 1943-1993
  - My Way of Looking at It: An Autobiography, 1980-1989
    - Correspondence, 1983-1989 (Folder 29: 7)
    - Brochure, 1983 (Folder 29: 8)
    - Printed copies (Folder 29: 9-10)
    - Proofs, 1983 (Folder 30: 1)
    - Draft, 1983 (Folder 30: 2-6)
    - Bulk mailing, 1983 (Folder 31: 1)
    - Copyright, 1983 (Folder 31: 2)
    - Foreword, 1983 (Folder 31: 3)
    - Mailing lists, 1983 (Folder 31: 4)
    - Mailing records, 1983 (Folder 31: 5)
    - Permissions, 1983 (Folder 31: 6)
    - Production, 1983 (Folder 31: 7)
    - Promotion, 1983-1986 (Folder 31: 8)
    - Publicity, 1983-1984 (Folder 31: 9)
    - Readers' correspondence, 1982 (Folder 32: 1)
    - Rejections, 1981-1982 (Folder 32: 2)
    - Releases, 1983 (Folder 32: 3)
    - Research, 1980-1982 (Folder 32: 4)
    - Review copies, 1983-1984 (Folder 32: 5)
    - Self-publishing, 1980 (Folder 32: 6)
    - Sources of lists, 1982-1983 (Folder 32: 7)
  - Sketches, correspondence, 1989 (Folder 32: 8)
  - "Acceleration: Curricular and Calendar Problems," printed copy, 1943 September (Folder 32: 9)
  - "Advice to Young Teacher Educators," draft, 1986 (Folder 32: 10)
  - "After the Bakke Decision: An Article-Editorial," printed copy, 1978 November (Folder 32: 11)
  - "The Allegory of Sir Max," draft and printed copy, 1980 (Folder 32: 12)
  - "The American Democratic Experiment," draft, 1970 (Folder 32: 13)
  - "American Youth Hostels," printed copy, 1940 May (Folder 32: 14)
  - "Andy," correspondence and draft, 1965 January (Folder 32: 15)
  - "ASCD and Social Realities," draft, 1993 (Folder 32: 16)
  - "ASCD at 50: Achievements and Opportunities," draft and printed copy, 1993 January33. (Folder 32: 17)
  - "Attitudes toward Publishing and Writing: A Survey of Alabama Teacher Educators," correspondence, draft, and printed copy, 1979 (Folder 33: 1)
  - "Building Intercultural Attitudes through the School," drafts and printed copy, 1949 January (Folder 33: 2)
  - "Back to Basics-With A Difference," correspondence, draft, and printed copy, 1975 October (Folder 33: 3)
  - "Better Curriculum-Better Discipline," correspondence and printed copy, 1956 September (Folder 33: 4)
  - "But Should We Indoctrinate?" printed copy, 1935 November (Folder 33: 5)
  - With Celia M. Stern, "Children's Literature and the Negro Stereotype," printed copy, 1945 February (Folder 33: 6)
  - "Combating Juvenile Delinquency through Schools," 1956 March (Folder 33: 7)
  - With Douglas S. Ward, "Consumer Education and the Social Studies," draft and printed copy, 1944 January 17 (Folder 33: 8)
  - Contributions to AYH Knapsack, drafts and printed copies, 1939-1946 (Folder 33: 9)
  - "A Conversation with William Van Til," printed copy, 1989 January (Folder 34: 1)
  - "Credo in Action," printed copy, 1952 January (Folder 34: 2)
  - "Critical Attitudes toward Teacher Education," correspondence and printed copy, 1955 (Folder 34: 3)
  - "The Crucial Issues in Secondary Education Today," correspondence, draft, and printed copy, 1976 April (Folder 34: 4)
  - "Curriculum Frontiers of the 1960's," printed copy, 1961-1962 (Folder 34: 5)
  - "Educational Technology and Professional Practice," draft, 1967 May (Folder 34: 6)
  - "Experiences Are Not Transplantable," printed copy, 1946 November (Folder 34: 7)
  - "A Fable of Textbook Strategy," printed copy, 1948 January (Folder 34: 8)
  - "Five Bold Ways to Attack the Dropout Problem," correspondence and drafts, 1965 March (Folder 34: 9)
  - "Future," draft, 1975 (Folder 34: 10)
  - "The Genuine Educational Frontiers," correspondence, draft, and printed copy, 1964 April 18 (Folder 34: 11)
  - "Great Debates in American Education," printed copy, 1953 January (Folder 35: 1)
  - "Gordon F. Vars: A Memoir," printed copy, 1993 January (Folder 35: 2)
  - "Hostel Vacation," drafts and printed copy, 1945 April (Folder 35: 3)
  - "How Not to Make an Assignment," correspondence and printed copy, 1964 October (Folder 35: 4)
  - "Improving Human Relations in the School Program," correspondence and proofs, 1956 October (Folder 35: 5)
  - "In the Age of Disbelief," correspondence, draft, and printed copy, 1980-1981 (Folder 35: 6)
  - "The Influence of Social Travel on Relations among High School Students," printed copy, 1944 March (Folder 35: 7)
  - "The Intellectually Gifted Child: A Review of Current (Folder 35: 8)
  - Approaches and Issues," printed copy, 1957 July (Folder 35:)
  - With George W. Denemark, "Intercultural Education," correspondence and printed copy, 1953 (Folder 35: 9)
  - "Intercultural Education Enters School Programs," draft, 1944 August 31 (Folder 35: 10)
  - "Is Progressive Education Obsolete?" correspondence, draft, and printed copy, 1962 February 17 (Folder 35: 11)
  - "The Issue in the Social Studies," draft, 1968 May (Folder 35: 12)
  - "Issues in Education," printed copy, 1977 February (Folder 35: 13)
  - "John L. Childs: An Appreciaton," draft, 1984 (Folder 36: 1)
  - "Junior High School or Middle School?" correspondence, drafts, and printed copy, 1970 April (Folder 36: 2)
  - "The Key Word Is Relevance," correspondence, draft, and printed copy, 1939 October (Folder 36: 3)
  - "The Making of Their Modern Minds: The Study of Public Opinion," printed copy, 1939 October (Folder 36: 4)
  - With John H. Lounsbury, "Meet Junior," correspondence and printed copy, 1957 December (Folder 36: 5)
  - "Moments That Made a Difference," correspondence, 1970 (Folder 36: 6)
  - "Orwell's 1984-Here? On the Way?" (Folder 36: 7)
  - "Publishing Opportunities: An Interview with William Van Til," correspondence and draft, 1980 (Folder 36: 8)
- Correspondence, 1959-1990
  - Houghton Mifflin, 1967-1979
    - General, 1969-1979 (Folder 36: 9)
    - Mehlinger, Howard, 1969-1973 (Folder 36: 10)
    - Possible authors, 1967-1969 (Folder 36: 11)
    - Revisions and future books, 1970-1974 (Folder 36: 12)
    - Stevens, Rich, 1968-1972 (Folder 36: 13)
      - 1973 (Folder 36: 14)
      - 1974 (Folder 36: 15)
      - 1975 (Folder 36: 16)
      - 1976 (Folder 37: 1)
      - 1977 (Folder 37: 2)
      - 1978 (Folder 37: 3)
    - Allyn & Bacon, 1980-1982 (Folder 37: 4)
    - Re: Another Way of Looking at It, 1975 (Folder 37: 5)
    - Bobbs-Merrill, 1959-1979 (Folder :)
    - General, 1972-1976 (Folder 37: 6)
    - Royalties, 1959-1979 (Folder 37: 7)
    - Boston publishers, 1977 (Folder 37: 8)
    - Comments on columns, 1970-1981 (Folder 37: 9)
    - Comments on dissertation, 1943-1946 (Folder 37: 10)
    - Contracts, 1964-1975 (Folder 37: 11)
    - The Educational Forum, 1990 (Folder 37: 12)
    - Elam, Stanley M., 1974-1982 (Folder 37: 13)
    - Journals in education, 1978 (Folder 37: 14)
    - McGraw-Hill, 1960-1963 (Folder 37: 15)
    - Permissions, 1979 (Folder 38: 1)
    - The Professional Educator, 1985-1991 (Folder 38: 2)
    - Writing for publication survey, 1973 (Folder 38: 3)
    - Writing rejected, 1971-1981 (Folder 38: 4)
    - Writing-requests to reprint, 1972-1979 (Folder 38: 5)
    - Writing workshops, 1977-1985
      - 1977-1978 (Folder 38: 6)
      - 1978-1982 (Folder 38: 7)
      - 1985 (Folder 38: 8)
- Speeches and Writings, 1935-1990
  - General, 1935-1981
    - Articles, 1935-1977
      - 1935-1964 (Folder 38: 9)
      - 1969-1977 (Folder 39: 1)
    - Columns, 1969-1975 (Folder 39: 2)
    - Editorials, 1961-1981 (Folder 39: 3)
    - Pamphlets and serial issues, 1935-1979
      - 1935-1945 (Folder 39: 4)
      - 1946-1955 (Folder 39: 5)
      - 1956-1963 (Folder 39: 6)
      - 1968-1971 (Folder 40: 1)
      - 1972-1979 (Folder 40: 2)
  - "Laboratory Schools and the National Reports," correspondence and drafts, 1984-1987 (Folder 40: 3)
  - "A Perception of the Economic Education Movement," draft and printed copy, 1974 (Folder 40: 4)
  - "Prejudiced-How Do People Get That Way?" correspondence and printed copy, 1956-1958 (Folder 40: 5)
  - "Restoring Honor to the Teaching Profession," correspondence and printed copy, 1989-1990 (Folder 40: 6)
  - "Should We Educate the Spirit in Our Public Schools?" printed copy, 1950 February 19 (Folder 40: 7)
  - Sketches, printed copy, 1989 (Folder 40: 8)
  - "Universities and Crises," correspondence, draft, and printed copy, 1968-1969 (Folder 40: 9)
  - "What Popular Magazines Say about Education," correspondence, 1949-1950 (Folder 40: 10)
  - "A Social Living Curriculum for Postwar Secondary Education: An Approach to Curriculum Development through Centers of Experience Derived from the Interaction of Values, Social Realities, and Needs," correspondence and printed copy of abstract, 1946 (Folder 41: 1)
  - "The Work of the Bureau for Intercultural Education," draft, 1945 (Folder 41: 2)
  - With Paul Diederich, "The Workshop," draft, 1945 (Folder 41: 3)
  - With R. Joseph Dixon, "Widening Cultural Horizons: Recommended Approaches to Intercultural Education," correspondence, draft, and printed copy, 1975 (Folder 41: 4)
  - "The Year 2000: Supervision," drafts, 1969 (Folder 41: 5)
  - "Schools of the Year 2000," draft and transparencies, 1969 (Folder 41: 6)
  - "The Year 2000: Teacher Education," 1968-1972 (Folder 41:)
  - Correspondence and draft, 1968-1970 (Folder 41: 7)
  - Correspondence, printed copy, and review, 1968-1972 (Folder 41: 8)
  - Introduction to Edward G. Olsen and Phillip A. Clark, Life-Centering Education, correspondence and draft, 1974-1977 (Folder 42: 1)
  - Foreword to Sidney B. Katz, Jerome T. Kapes, and Perry A. Zirkel, Resources for Writing for Publication in Education, correspondence and proof, 1979 (Folder 42: 2)
  - Foreword to issue of Thresholds in Education, correspondence, draft, and printed copy, 1986 November (Folder 42: 3)
  - Foreword to issue of Thresholds in Education, correspondence and printed copy, 1988 May (Folder 42: 4)
  - "After the Bakke Decision: An Article-Editorial," printed copy, 1978 November (Folder 42: 5)
  - "A Question of Values," printed copy, 1961 May (Folder 42: 6)
  - "In a Time of Value Crises," draft, 1972 October (Folder 42: 7)
  - "Now It's 'How' and 'When'-Not 'Whether'," correspondence and printed copy, 1955 November (Folder 42: 8)
  - "Curriculum Improvement: Who Participates?" draft and printed copy, 1954 March (Folder 42: 9)
  - "On William Heard Kilpatrick," draft and printed copy, 1966 January (Folder 42: 10)
  - "Planning Intercultural Education," draft and printed copy, 1946 January (Folder 42: 11)
  - "What Are the Real 'Basics' in Education?" printed copy, 1962 November (Folder 42: 12)
  - "The Task of Intercultural Education," 1945 December (Folder 42: 13)
  - Introduction to Russell L. Hamm and William E. Brownson,The Arenas of Power: Focus on Schooling, 1977 (Folder 42: 14)
  - Preface to Lewis and Rae Harris, Bootstraps: A Chronicle of a Real Community School, correspondence and draft, 1980 (Folder 42: 15)
- Journals edited by William Van Til, 1946-1984
  - Intercultural Education News, printed copies, 1946-1947 (Folder 42: 16)
  - Phi Delta Kappan, 1970